Halifax, Mass. Congregational Church records, 1734-1932.
Congregational Library & Archives
Halifax, Mass. Congregational Church records, 1734-1932.
RG5192
Congregational Library & Archives
1.09 Cubic Feet
(1 box)
A Congregational church was officially formed in Halifax in 1734, with 53 founding members. A second meeting house was built in 1852. In 1842 a Ladies Sewing Circle was organized and continued to be central to church life. The Halifax Congregational Church is now a member of the United Church of Christ, and continues to serve the community today. This collection consists of early administrative records for the Congregational Church and the associated parish in Halifax.
Church of Christ (Halifax, Mass.)
Halifax Congregational Church (Halifax, Mass.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were loaned to the Congregational Library & Archives by Halifax Congregational Church, in March 2019; 2014-41.
Historical Note
The land which would become Halifax, Mass. was originally part of West Precinct of Plymouth, which included Plympton, Carver, and Wareham. In 1731, residents in northern Plympton lobbied successfully for permission to hold their own religious meeting in the home of Deacon Robert Waterman. The following year, local landowner John Bryant deeded a plot to the religious society's proprietors for the erection of a meeting house. In October of 1734 a church was officially formed by order of an ecclesiastical council, and its covenant signed by 22 male and 31 female members. Rev. John Cotton was the church's first minister, ordained in 1735 and remaining in the position for 20 years. Subsequent early pastors included Rev. William Patten (1757-1765), Rev. Ephraim Briggs (1767-1799), and Rev. Abel Richmond (1800-1832), who was ousted after a 33-year pastorate due to disagreements with parishioners.
A Sunday school was founded in 1736, possibly the first such establishment in North America. In the 1750s the meeting house was deemed too small to accommodate the growing population. The building was split in half and expanded by 16 feet in the middle. In addition to being a locus for both town and church business, the meeting house was also used for the storage of munitions and gunpowder during the latter part of the 18th century. In 1821 a steeple and bell were built and installed via funds raised from the sale of pews. The expanded first meeting house continued to serve the needs of the church until the early 1850s, when it was sold to the town to be used as a town hall. Though remarkably long-lived, the building was destroyed in a fire in 1907.
After the dismission of Rev. Abel Richmond in 1832, Rev. Eldridge Howe was invited to the ministry and accepted. A large portion of the congregation still professed loyalty to Rev. Richmond. In 1834, 15 members seceded from the church. This was followed by numerous other secessions over the following year, resulting in a significant decline in overall membership, to about half of its former size. The remaining congregants were unable to pay Rev. Howe's salary to his satisfaction, and he tendered his resignation in late 1835. The following decades were typified by short supply ministries, a notable exception being the 11-year pastorate of Rev. Timothy Brainerd from 1855-1866.
In 1842 a Ladies' "Missionary Sewing Circle" was officially organized, with the intent to provide clothing for a missionary station in Canada. The group changed names several times in subsequent years and was also known as the Ladies Sewing Circle, the Ladies Benevolent Society, and the Halifax Benevolent Society. Their mission also expanded to include general fundraising for the church and other charitable causes. Despite changes in name and emphasis, this women's group essentially persisted throughout the 19th and 20th centuries and remained an important part of church life.
In 1852 a second meeting house was built for the Church's use, slightly to the west of the original building. It was erected at a cost of $5,200 and was dedicated on December 7, 1852 with its dedicatory sermon delivered by the Rev. Charles Porter from Plymouth. In 1921, during Sunday service, a violent wind gust caused the steeple to collapse and the spire to fall into an unoccupied pew. The mortgage for the church was paid in full in 1978, and subsequently burned ceremonially in a special service, a popular tradition at the time. The Halifax Congregational Church is now a member of the United Church of Christ, and continues to serve the community today.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of early administrative records for the Congregational Church and the associated parish in Halifax, as well as membership records, records of Ladies' societies associated with the church, and manuscript historical narratives. Member records include a large number of marriage intentions from the early to mid 1800s.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into four series, listed below. Except within the membership series, records have been arranged in chronological order, by start date. Within the membership series, records have been grouped by topics, and further divided by either alphabetical or chronological order.
Bibliography
250th Anniversary Celebration: United Church of Christ of Halifax. Halifax, 1982. 17.11.1 H 13.5P H
Davis, Emerson. Biographical Sketches of the Congregational Pastors of New England: Volume II, n.d. 9.3.90
Perkins, Ruth V. 250th Anniversary of the Beginning of the Church. Halifax, 1982. 17.11.1 H 13.5P
Wadsworth, Joseph III. The History of the Halifax Congregational Church of Halifax, Massachusetts, Vol. 1 Halifax, 2008. 17.11.1 H 13.5 HalCC HW 2008
Church discipline.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Covenants (Church polity).; Marriage records.; Ordination.; Registers of births, etc.; Women -- Religious life.; Women -- Societies and clubs.; Church of Christ (Halifax, Mass.); Halifax (Mass.: Town) -- Church history.; Halifax Congregational Church (Halifax, Mass.)
- Church and parish records, 1734 1932; 1734-1932
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the administrative records of the church and parish in Halifax, including three bound records books. The series includes meeting minutes, officer lists, financial records, ecclesiastical council records, correspondence, and other administrative documentation.
  - Church records, 1734 1835; 1734-1835 (Box 1, Volume 1)
    This bound volume of church records contains the earliest administrative documentation of the Church of Christ in Halifax. It includes the church's confession of faith, the earliest covenant, meeting minutes, baptisms, member lists, and disciplinary records.
  - Officer lists, 1735 1885; 1735-1885 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    This file contains loose records documenting lists of church officers, including deacons and clergy.
  - Financial records, 1795 1844; 1795-1844 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    This folder contains loose financial records, including itemized receipts to and from various individuals for everyday expenses, and Rev. Abel Richmond's receipts for payments to Rhode Island College.
  - Parish records, 1824 1885; 1824-1885 (Box 1, Volume 3)
    This bound parish record book primarily contains meeting minutes, as well as policy documents, copies of deeds, and copies of correspondence.
  - Parish treasury records, 1825 1867; 1825-1867 (Box 1, Volume 4)
    This bound volume of parish treasury records contains financial ledgers with lists of subscribers and rates.
  - Ecclesiastical council records, 1832 1875; 1832-1875 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    This folder contains loose records containing the results of ecclesiastical councils, which were primarily called to settle disputes within individual churches, as well as for the ordinations of new ministers.
  - Meeting minutes, 1832 1878; 1832-1878 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    This folder contains loose records of meeting minutes for both the church and parish of Halifax, which include legal warnings, synopses of meetings, and votes on various issues.
  - Church records, 1832 1891; 1832-1891 (Box 1, Volume 5)
    This bound volume contains records for the Congregational Church in Halifax (referred to only as the "Church in Halifax"). The volume includes meeting minutes, baptisms, admissions, member lists, articles of faith, the church covenant, and ecclesiastical council minutes.
  - Correspondence, 1833 1932; 1833-1932 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    This folder contains loose correspondence, including letters relating to church disputes, missionary society correspondence and newsletter items, and invitations to ordination councils.
  - Photographs and prints, 1867; undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    This folder contains two black and white photographic prints depicting the sanctuary of the second meeting house and the downstairs sunday school room, an engraving of the Halifax town hall, and a missionary card depicting the ship "Morning Star".
  - Conference records, 1884; undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    This folder contains 2 loose records relating to the Pilgrim Conference at Halifax and an invitation to a the Boston Council of Congregational Churches.
  - Policy documents, 1919; undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    This folder contains loose records relating to church policy, including undated early copies of the church's articles of faith and covenant, as well as a constitution document from the National Council of the Congregational Churches of the United States.
- Membership records, 1788 1895; 1788-1895
  This series contains the membership records of the church in Halifax, and includes lists of admissions to the church, formal correspondence relating to dismissions and transfers to and from other churches, a large number of official marriage intention documents from the 1800s, and several relations of faith by potential members.
  - Dismissions and transfers (A-H), 1788 1891; 1788-1891 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    This folder contains official correspondence between churches, relating to the transfer and dismission of members to and from the Congregational Church in Halifax. It includes documentation relating to members with surnames A-H.
  - Dismissions and transfers (I-Z), 1822 1895; 1822-1895 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    This folder contains official correspondence between churches, relating to the transfer and dismission of members to and from the Congregational Church in Halifax. It includes documentation relating to members with surnames I-Z.
  - Marriage intentions (A-B), 1804 1849; 1804-1849 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    This folder contains marriage intentions, official documents recording marriages in Halifax and surrounding areas. The intentions record the names of the betrothed and their location, and are typically signed by the town clerk. Records are arranged alphabetically by the groom's surname.
    Marriage intentions by surname, A-B
    Melzar Adams Jr. and Olive Inglee
    1804 (Halifax)
    1804 (Kingston)
    Daniel Alden and Joanna Tilson
    1804
    Seth Allen and Lucy Holmes
    1809
    Sidney Allen and Elizabeth Hayward
    1849
    John Attwood Jr. and Martha Thomson
    1828
    Jabez Bosworth and Sarah Bradford
    1806
    Francis Bourne and Jannet Thomson
    1823
    William Bozworth and Lucy Hayward
    1807
    Zalmon Brigg and Mary Briggs
    1819
    Thomas Bryant and Nancy Sturtevant
    1827
    Zenas Bryant and Judith Sturtevant
    1822
    Robert Byram and Mercy Faxon
    1814
  - Marriage intentions (C-G), 1802 1827; 1802-1827 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Marriage intentions by surname, C-G
    Sebery Child Hathaway and Sarah Porter
    1818
    Ebenezer Colwell Jr. and Elizabeth Bosworth
    Galen Colwell and Lucy Bosworth
    1827 (West Bridgewater)
    1827 (Plympton)
    Isaac Cook and Jane Drew
    1802
    Thomas Cornish and Deborah Leach
    1826 (Halifax)
    1826 (Plymouth)
    Melven Crooker and Mary Thomson
    George Drew and Sarah Thomson III
    1810
    Silvanus Eddy and Joanna Fuller Jr.
    1808
    Nathaniel French and Betsey Waterman
    1811
    Nathaniel French and Eliza Waterman
    Benjamin Fuller and Anne Bosworth
    1826
    Ebenezer Fuller and Rebecca Fuller
    Thomas Fuller and Sally Sturtevant
  - Marriage intentions (H), 1802 1839; 1802-1839 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Marriage intentions by surname, H
    Benjamin Hammonds and Hannah Sturtevant
    1802 (Carver)
    1802 (Halifax)
    Ebenezer Hall and Nancy Dunbar
    1816 (Halifax)
    1816 (Bridgewater)
    Silvanus Hall and Almiry Cushman
    Silvanus Hall and Almaria Cushman
    John Harris and Rebecca Wood
    1811 (Bridgewater)
    1811 (Halifax)
    Ephraim Harden and Harty Harden
    Ebenezer Hathaway and Lucia Hill
    1839
    Benjamin Hayward and Cynthia Wade
    1831
    Ziba Hayward and Sally Bozworth
    Ziba Hayward and Sarah Bosworth III
    Eleazer Holmes and Ruth Waterman
    1803
    Ellis Holmes and Content Chipman
    1808 (Brigewater)
    1808 (Halifax)
  - Marriage intentions (J-M), 1801 1848; 1801-1848 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Marriage intentions by surname, J-M
    George Washington Jackson and Molly Briggs Jr.
    William Jackson to Joanna Crooker
    1848
    Ebenezer Johnson and Lucinda Sears
    1826 (Londonderry)
    Arnold Leach and Polly Fuller
    1812 (Middleborough)
    1812 (Halifax)
    Joseph Leach and Susanna Sturtevant
    1801 (Halifax)
    1801 (Middleboro)
    Joshua Leach and Celia Dean
    Alpha Lyon and Tabatha Leach
    1829
    Isaac Lyon and Polly Thomson
    1816
    Joshua Lyon and Lucy Thomson
    Albert Morton and Rachel Hadley
    1825
    Cyrus Morton and Lucy Drew
    Lloyd Morton and Mercy Tilson
    1820
  - Marriage intentions (P-R), 1801 1832; 1801-1832 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Marriage intentions by surname, P-R
    Friend Perkins and Anna Inglee
    1832
    John Pool and Bethiah Lucas
    Henry Pope and Lydia Sturtevant
    Asa Pratt and Lydia Lyon
    Asa Pratt II and Rebecca Leach
    Bela Pratt and Sophia Weston
    1801
    Cornelius Pratt and Lucina Thompson
    1823 (Bridgewater)
    1823 (Halifax)
    David Pratt and Lydia Corthell
    1812
    Ebenezer Pratt and Olive Wood
    1824
    Jonathan Pratt and Nabby Phillips
    Samuel Ramsdel Jr. and Rebecca Thompson
    Isaiah Ripley Jr. and Zerviah Fuller
    1805 (Plympton)
    1805 (Halifax)
  - Marriage intentions (S), 1801 1848; 1801-1848 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Marriage intentions by surname, S
    William Seares and Mary Wood
    James Smith and Mercy Colwell
    1847
    Daniel Soule and Lucy Waterman
    1818 (Plympton)
    1818 (Halifax)
    Ebenezer Soule and Mary Thompson
    1828 (Dorchester)
    Ebenezer Soule and Mary Thomson
    1828 (Halifax)
    isaac Soule and Ruth Fuller
    1805
    Thomas Soule and Betsy Soule
    Thomas Standish and Bethiah Waterman
    John Stebbins and Mary Ford
    Thomas Stilman and Claira Thomson
    Bela Sturtevant and Hannah Chandler
    Dependence Sturtevant and Sarah Soule
    John Sturtevant and Martha Waterman
    Josiah Sturtevant and Charlotte Cushing
    Ward Sturtevant and Lucinda Christian
  - Marriage intentions (T), 1801 1826; 1801-1826 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Marriage intentions by surname, T
    Walter Thomas and Fanny Clark
    1815 (Halifax)
    1815 (Plympton)
    Eliab Thomson and Levina Washburn
    1819 (Halifax)
    1819 (Bridgewater)
    Ire Thomson and Sophie Drew
    Eliab Thomson and Lydia Thomson`
    Lewis Thomson and Huldah Wood
    1821
    Nathan Thomson and Elizabeth Fobes
    1802 (Bridgewater)
    Nathaniel Thomson and Molly Foster
    Ward Thomson and Molly Holmes
    Adam Tomson Jr. and Salvina Wood Jr.
    Nathan Tomson and Elizabeth Fobes
    Samuel Tomson and Clare Sturlevant
    1801`
    Zebadiah Tomson Jr. and Martha Briggs
    Bethuel Tilson and Pemela Bosworth
    Bethuel Tillson and Peranelia Bosworth
  - Marriage intentions (W), 1802 1826; 1802-1826 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Marriage intentions by surname, W
    James Wade and Sabina Lyon
    Melven Wade and Lydia Holmes
    Cephas Washburn and Mercy Parris
    1826 (Bridgewater)
    Cephas Waterman and Bathsheba Richmond
    Abial White and Joanna Fuller
    Martin Willis and Sabina Thompson
    Cyrus Wood and Lucy Fuller
    John Wood and Dianthy Waterman
    Judah Wood Jr. and Rhoda Shaw
    Timothy Wood Jr. and Mercy Bosworth Jr.
  - Admissions, 1840 1867; 1840-1867 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    This folder contains loose records relating to admissions, specifically lists of admitted members with dates of admission. Some documents recording early admissions appear to be in a more modern hand.
  - Relations, 1842 1867; 1842-1867 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    This folder contains relations of faith documents, formalized personal religious statements written by individuals seeking admission to the church. The relations are organized alphabetically by surname.
    Relations by surname
    Bosworth, Mary
    undated
    Fuller, Mary
    1858
    Fuller, Levesta
    1863
    1867
    1867 (copy)
    Fuller, Nelson
    1861
    Morton, Lydia
    1842
    Sturtevant, Mary
    Sylvester, L. H.
    1869
    Thomson, Salvina
- Historical narratives, 1807-1812, undated
  This series contains handwritten historical accounts, mainly by Halifax local Ignatius Thomson. In his voluminous manuscripts he describes the historical events leading up to the foundation of Halifax as well as a history of the town and region. There are also a small number of undated handwritten historical notes.
  - Ignatius Thomson historical manuscript and ledger, 1807 1812; 1807-1812 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    This manuscript volume contains a broad-ranging historical narrative focusing on the history of Halifax. A tête-bêche financial ledger is also present at the back of the volume.
  - Ignatius Thomson historical manuscripts (loose), undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    These loose manuscript pages were removed from the Ignatius Thomson historical manuscript and ledger, 1807-1812, and contain similar historical narrative material.
  - Historical narratives, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    This folder contains undated historical notes relating to the history of Halifax, including a handwritten historical sketch, and part of an unidentified published tract.
- Ladies Societies records, 1842 1890; 1842-1890
  This series consists of four record books and one folder of loose documents relating to various iterations of the Ladies Society of the Halifax Congregational Church. The record books are largely sequential with occassional gaps and changes in name.
  - Ladies Benevolent Society records, 1842 1855; 1842-1855 (Box 1, Volume 6)
    This record book of the Ladies Benevolent Society contains a preamble with the organization's mission statement, meeting minutes, lists of officers, lists of subscribers, and financial records.
  - Ladies Benevolent Society records, 1855 1863; 1855-1863 (Box 1, Volume 7)
    This volume contains the records for the Ladies Benevolent Society, including meeting minutes, officer lists, financial records, and records of charitable contributions including collections for Union soldiers during the Civil War.
  - Ladies Sewing Society records (loose), 1860-1864; undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    This folder of loose records relating to the Ladies Sewing Society were found inside the Ladies Benevolent Society record book, 1855-1863. They include correspondence, including a letter relating to Civil War charity donations, and financial records.
  - Ladies Sewing Society records, 1873 1881; 1873-1881 (Box 1, Volume 8)
    This bound volume of Ladies Sewing Society records includes a copy of the organization's constitution, meeting minutes, officer lists, and financial ledgers.
  - Ladies Sewing Circle records, 1881 1890; 1881-1890 (Box 1, Volume 9)
    This bound volume of the Ladies Sewing Circle records includes meeting minutes, officer lists, and copies of correspondence.